Guide to the Bonner and Howard families papers, 1900-2012 MS 627
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Bonner and Howard Families papers
1900-2012
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Turner, Sandy Howard
MS 627
12 Linear Feet 14 boxes
Photographs, correspondence, business records, diaries, scrapbooks and more, documenting the family and business lives of the Bonner and Howard families in Texas in the 20th century.
Biographical / Historical
Benjamin Franklin Bonner, son of William Henry and Matilda Blackburn Bonner, was born April 14, 1869 in Angelina County, TX. During his youth he operated his parent's ferry on the Neches River while attending school in Angelina County, and then became a correspondent for the Houston Post and Galveston News and involved with the lumber and mercantile business. In 1894 he cames to Houston as president of the Joe Davis Oil Co., organized Southwestern Oil Co., and established the first oil refinery in Houston and the first lubricating plant in the South. In 1901 Bonner organized the Bonner Oil Co. and in 1904 became vice president and general manager of the Kirby Lumber Co., rising to president from 1919 to 1923. He assisted Robert W. Wier organizing and incorporating the R.W. Wier Lumber Co. in 1907 and the Wier Long Leaf Lumber Co. and Gulf & Northern Railway in 1917, serving as president until 1926. From then until 1944 he served as vice president and a director of the Wier Long Leaf Lumber Co. and R.W. Wier Lumber Co. He helped organize the San Jacinto Trust Co. and San Jacinto National Bank and served as vice president of the trust company and a director of the bank. Service also included a director of the Houston Belt & Terminal Railway and board member of the Methodist Hospital, Houston. He married Annie Wier on April 22, 1891 and had two daughters, Garland (Mrs. George Howard) and Annie Wier (Mrs. Sheppard W. King). He died in Houston on Feb. 29, 1944.
Scope and Contents
Photographs, correspondence, business records, diaries, scrapbooks and more, documenting the family and business lives of the Bonner and Howard families in Texas in the 20th century.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by the family, via Sandy Howard Turner, Feb. 20, 2015.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series: Series I: Benjamin Franklin Bonner and Annier Wier Bonner; Series II: Garland Bonner Howard; Series III: George Francis Howard; Series IV: Frank Bonner Howard; Series V: Family; Series VI: Photographs/albums
Index Terms
Subjects
Business enterprises -- Texas -- Houston; Businessmen
Document Types
letters (correspondence); photographs; scrapbooks; business records
- Series I: Benjamin Franklin Bonner & Annie Wier Bonner, 212790
  - B.F. Bonner, 212791
    - Biography, 212792 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Investments, 212793 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Sinclair Prairie Oil Market Co., 212794 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Angelina County land, 212795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Land sale for First National Bank, 212840 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - LaPorte bay house, 212798 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Will, 1942; 212796 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Trust, 1951; 212797 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Obituary, 1944; 213216 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Edna Ewing Bonner - will, 1940; 212957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bonner Motor Co., 1941; 212958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: W.M. Vinson Jr., 212959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: T.P. Wier Jr., 212960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - R.W. Wier Lumber Co., 212962 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Wier Long Leaf Lumber Co., 212963 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Estate ledger, 1920s-1950s; 212799 (Box 3)
    - Estate cash book, 1944-49; 212800 (Box 4)
    - Trust cash book, 1950-56; 212801 (Box 4)
  - Annie Wier Bonner, 212802
    - Travel diary, 1926; 212803 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Silver pieces listing, 1938; 212804 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Legal: Annie Wier Bonner v. Charles A. Fritzsche, 1940; 212805 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Legal: Sale of Winkler Rd. property, 1939; 212808 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Obituary, 213217 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series II: Garland Bonner Howard, 213030
  - Notsuoh, 1912; 213031 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Property with R.A. Piehl, 213032 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Rose Survey property sale, 213033 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Promissory notes, 213034 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Barber Survey parcel, 1969; 213035 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Satsuma Gardens deed of trust, 1952; 213036 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - West Edgemont addition warranty deed, 213037 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Sales agreement, 1970; 213039 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Estate, 1975; 213040 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Estate tax return, 1975; 213041 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Inheritance tax return, 1975; 213042 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Daily record, n.d.; 213043 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Daily calendar, 1911; 213044 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Journal ledger, 1949-50; 213045 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Income taxes (individually and with George F. Howard), 1933-44; 213046 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Income taxes (individually and with George F. Howard), 1945-66; 213047 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series III: George Francis Howard, 213048
  - Correspondence: personal, 213049 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Margaret Compton, 213050 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: House of Representatives, 213051 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, 213052 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Property sale to R.A. Piehl and Garland B. Howard, 1940; 213053 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Broadacres purchase with others, 1924; 213054 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Jackson and Wharton counties property, 213055 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Legal: Blackshear v. Vaughn, 1930s; 213056 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Houston Clinic loan, 1941; 213057 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - C.A. Coskey estate, 213058 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - House of Representatives resolution, 1951; 213060 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Estate, 1952; 213059 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Frank Bonner Howard, 213061
  - Financial statement, 213062 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Income taxes, 213063 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Financial, 213065 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Ranger Oil Co., LA producing properties, 213067 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Howard no. 5 well, Harris Co., 213066 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Coastal Bond & Mortgage Co., 213068 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Callahan & Vince Survey parcel sale, 1974; 213069 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Estate, 1979; 213070 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Trust, 1933; 213071 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Meadowbrook subdivision, 213073
    - Land, 213074 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Mortgage, 213083 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Abtract of Title, 213075 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Property sales/conveyances, 213076 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Bliss Meadows, 213077 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Plats, 213078 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Gulf Frwy. & WInkler tracts marketing, 213079 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Meadowbrook Lumber Co., 213084
      - Legal & financial, 213085 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Financial statement, 213086 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Meadowbrook Development Co., 213088
      - Financial statement, 1971; 213089 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Stock, 213090 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Deed of Trust, Garland B. & Frank B. Howard, co-trustees, 1959; 213091 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Annie Wier Bonner King account, 213092 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Meadowbrook Transportation Co., 213093 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Frank B. Howard affidavit, 1970; 213094 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Frank Howard Homes, Inc., 213064
      - Taxes, 213095 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Substitute trustee's deed, 1963; 213096 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Appointment of substitute trustee, 1970; 213097 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Easement, 1940s-60s; 213098 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Houston Lighting & Power easement, 213099 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Ellington Field housing, 213120 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Howard Freeway Shopping Center income tax, 1975; 213121 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 213122 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Field notes, 213143 (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Series V: Family, 213133
  - George Bonner Howard: American Teachers Insurance Co., 1969; 213134 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Joyce Z. Howard v. Charles A. Coskey Jr., 1984; 213135 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Annie Wier Bonner King: insurance, 213136 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Annie Wier Bonner King estate, 1950s; 213137 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Shepherd W. King correspondence, 213139 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Shepherd W. King business, 213138 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Shepherd W. King III Trust, 213140 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: D.S. Wier re: Shephard King III, 213141 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: C.C. Wier, 213142 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Memorabilia, 213144 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Various estates, 213145 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Photographs / albums, 213149
  - Garland B. Howard travel photo album [Europe], 1925; 213150 (Box 11)
  - George & Garland Howard travel photo album [Mexico & Canada], 213187 (Box 12)
  - Garland Howard scrapbook/photo album: Mexico... bay house, Branard house, Lauderdale house [school days], 213188 (Box 13)
  - Garland Howard scrapbook, ca. 1909; 213194 (Box 13)
  - Loose scrapbook pages & items, 213195 (Box 13)
  - Glenbrook Golf Club album photos by Calvin Wheat (Box 13)
  - Individual photographs, 213196 (Box 14)
    - B.F. Bonner, 213197 (Box 14)
    - Garland Bonner Howard, 213198 (Box 14)
    - Garland Bonner as Queen of Notsuoh, 1912; 213199 (Box 14)
    - Alfred Howard, 213200 (Box 14)
    - Garland B. Howard & Frank B. Howard, 213201 (Box 14)
    - George F. Howard, 213202 (Box 14)
    - Annie Wier Bonner King, 213203 (Box 14)
    - Patricia King, 213204 (Box 14)
    - Garland B. Howard with others, 213205 (Box 14)
    - Nancy Howard, 213206 (Box 14)
    - A. Ryland Howard, 213207 (Box 14)
    - George F. Howard, William Ward Watkin, Garland B. Howard, Frank B. Howard; Alhambra, Toledo Spain, 1925, 213208 (Box 14)
    - B. F. Bonner grave, Glenwood Cemetery, Houston, 213209 (Box 14)
    - Garland Bonner's horse, "Sunbeam", 213210 (Box 14)
    - B.F. Bonner bay house "Angelina," Laporte, TX, 213211 (Box 14)
    - B.F. Bonner house, 1900 Main, Houston, 213212 (Box 14)
    - Lufkin, TX, 1888; 213213 (Box 14)
    - unidentified, 213214 (Box 14)